War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese [music] aircraft
attacked the American naval base at
Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history [music] of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who [music] could no longer
meet
the price [music] of empire.
Whatever justifications for their
actions were advanced then or have been
advanced since,
the facts cannot be disputed.
War that consumed the world was started
by German and Japanese acts of
aggression.
And now it is 1944.
Germany and Japan are being driven from
the lands that they have conquered.
They face a desperate defense of their
own territory.
And the prospect of unconditional
surrender.
Late in 1944, the winter had stopped the
Allied advance north through Italy short
of Bologna.
With spring, the offensive would be
resumed.
>> All of a sudden, these Germans were
flying over us dropping pamphlets.
10th Mountain Division, welcome.
You will be all killed. You will never
come back alive to your country.
Put scare into you.
>> Mark Clark's 15th Army Group comprising
the 5th US and 8th British Armies
would drive the Germans into the
mountains. Italy was the costliest
campaign waged by Anglo-American forces
against Germany.
>> I remember this German bunker that must
have been hit with an artillery shell.
And this German was yelling for help.
One of the guys is going over with a
grenade.
He pulls a pin and throws it right in
there.
Boom.
Everything was quiet.
I tried to stop him, you know, but maybe
it was a in a way he was right.
>> Mark Clark planned to catch and squeeze
German Army Group C between his two
armies.
By now, Italians in the form of partisan
brigades were fighting with the allies.
Replacements for Canadian troops that
had been withdrawn to join the Normandy
invasion force.
The campaign began [music] with Indians
and New Zealanders
attacking on the 9th of April, followed
by other Eighth Army units attempting to
turn the flank of the German 10th Army.
>> Good progress made and many prisoners
taken by men who, though crowded out of
the headlines, are most certainly not a
forgotten army.
>> The US Fifth Army, General Truscott, was
delayed [music] by bad weather and
joined the offensive on April 14th.
In the center, Second Polish Corps
crossed the Sillaro and began forging
ahead along Route 9.
Bologna fell on the 21st.
Modena and Ferrara in the next couple of
days.
On the 23rd,
General von Vietinghoff,
who had been encouraged to make peace
[music] overtures by Heinrich Himmler
himself,
agreed that an approach should be made
to the allies without reference to
Berlin.
But by the time an Allied representative
had received authorization to negotiate,
>> [music]
>> the offensive had an almost unstoppable
momentum.
The Americans
reached to Genoa on April the 27th.
On the 29th, the Germans, acting without
authorization from Berlin,
signed an unconditional surrender.
The war in Italy was over.
>> That was that. Unconditional surrender
of nearly a million men signed away by
German officers in sports coats.
>> On the same [music] day, but on the
other side of the world,
the formation that was longer in
front-line service than any other in the
British Army, the 17th Indian Division,
>> [music]
>> entered Pegu as part of the final
assault on Burma's capital,
Rangoon.
Two operations designed [music] to expel
the Japanese from Burma had been
underway for several months.
Capital, in which Slim's 14th Army
advanced from Assam across the Chindwin,
[music] reestablishing contact with the
Nationalist Chinese,
and Dracula, a combined airborne,
[music]
land, and amphibious assault on Rangoon.
Operation Capital had been launched on
December 3rd.
General Kimura, commanding Japan's Burma
Area Army,
was in a threadbare situation with
little prospect of resupply.
Obliged to marshal what he had with
great care, he fell back before the
initial advance, offering token
resistance.
This lack of stubborn defense encouraged
Slim to change the plan.
Operation Extended Capital was more
ambitious.
It envisaged a race south to seize a
port, Moulmein or Rangoon, before the
onset of the monsoon.
By mid-January, the 19th Indian Division
had established a bridgehead across the
Irrawaddy. At the end of the month, the
Burma and Ledo roads were joined at
Mongyu. The Chinese First Army now
striking south along the Burma Road, the
6th making for Bhamo's southeast.
IV Corps pressed south initiating the
battle for Meiktila, which fell to the
17th Indian Division.
Its supply route was cut by a Japanese
counterattack.
The veteran 17th had to rely on
air-dropped supplies,
repelling repeated attempts by the
Japanese 33rd Army to take Meiktila's
airfields.
The 33rd's commander, General Masaki
Honda, was forced to order a withdrawal
on March 28th, by which time Mandalay
had fallen.
>> By late April the first promise of the
monsoon, the so-called mango rains, were
falling.
It was decided to go ahead with the
combined Allied assault on Rangoon.
>> When we got near Rangoon,
the rains came.
You can't believe it,
but within one night,
the fields were full of water and the
treetop was visible. Otherwise, the
truck was not there.
So, you couldn't move.
>> The Gurkha Parachute Battalion dropped
onto Elephant Point on May 1st.
The 26th Indian Division made the
amphibious [music] assault the next day,
but there was nothing to assault.
The Japanese [music] had withdrawn the
day before.
>> The Japs, apparently,
used to go for these gold teeth.
Used to have gold teeth, a lot of them.
You come across dead Japs, you had to
search them.
See what identification on tell who you
were.
The chap [music] that we had in the West
Kents,
he used to look at them
and collect their teeth.
He got little bag, gold teeth. Now, this
is true. I'm not making this up.
>> By the beginning of August, the The
Japanese had withdrawn from Burma, but
they were not pursued.
Because by August 1945,
Allied troops were on Japanese soil.
The opening campaign of 1945,
pushing back the Co-Prosperity Sphere,
had been the conquest of the
Philippines.
It had started with Leyte, then moved to
the main island of Luzon,
where the first landings had occurred at
the beginning of January.
The landings were virtually unopposed,
but offshore,
the activity was destructive.
Kamikaze was an effective use of
obsolete machines and only partially
trained pilots.
The Japanese dispatched waves of
Kamikaze, which damaged [music] many
ships.
The Kamikaze slogan was one plane, one
warship.
They did not prevent the Sixth Army
General Walter Krueger from establishing
itself in the north of Luzon.
14th Corps struck Lingayen, First Corps
alongside struck Rosario and met fierce
resistance before breaking out. 11th
Corps landed north of Bataan on January
29th, 11th Airborne at the entrance to
Manila Bay 2 days later. In Tokyo, Prime
Minister Koiso admitted to the
parliament that
"Military developments are in a state
which does not necessarily admit of
optimism."
14th Corps reached the outskirts of
Manila on February 3rd and General
Douglas MacArthur announced that the
capital had fallen.
He was wrong.
Japanese resistance in Manila did not
end until March 3rd, by which time
Krueger's Sixth Army had taken 6,500
casualties and the Filipino capital had
been reduced to rubble.
An estimated 100,000 Filipinos were
killed.
The Japanese could hardly doubt their
fate [music] and vengefully took a
terrible toll on the civilian population
>> [music]
>> in a criminal terror for which their
overall commander, the storied Tiger of
[music] Malaya, would be held
responsible.
>> So that if your marshal it is
responsible
in any measure
for the violations of the laws of war
committed by the men under his command
in the Philippines
anything less than the death sentence
would be a mockery.
>> General Tomoyuki Yamashita was hanged
for war crimes.
Many Japanese troops remained in strong
defensive positions throughout [music]
the Philippines.
They were effectively ignored.
Impotent players in a war that had moved
on to storm the two fortified outposts
that now stood between the allies and
the Japanese home islands.
Iwo Jima
and Okinawa.
More than 1,200 km south of [music]
Tokyo, one of the volcano group of
islands, Iwo Jima,
has an area of just over 20 square
kilometers.
In early 1944, [music] Major General
Tadamichi Kuribayashi
and the 21,000 men of the 109th Division
had been sent to turn Iwo Jima [music]
into an impregnable fortress and to
defend it.
Kuribayashi was seen off by the emperor
[music] in person.
He was not expected to return to Japan.
The allies were now starting to transfer
troops from Europe.
On the morning of February the 19th, the
first wave of the men of the 3rd, 4th,
and 5th Marine Divisions landed.
>> The Japanese had a way of making
underwater swimmers,
strap a bomb on their head,
swim underwater, and
bounce their head into the ship.
And we had to stand over the rail with
rifles to shoot them as they were coming
towards the ship.
>> Kuribayashi's plan was to hold fire
until the beach was congested with
Marines and all their equipment.
>> Iwo Jima was a tough battle because of
the Mount Suribachi,
they were bombarding it, but they
weren't making any progress
because of the tunnels that were dug
there.
>> The Japanese had prepared strong
defensive positions, well-placed machine
guns installed in bunkers,
heavy artillery protected behind
reinforced steel doors firing from the
high ground.
The Marines were ready for suicide
banzai attacks, but these did not come.
Kuribayashi, who believed them to be
wasteful, had forbidden them.
As the battle ground on, the Japanese
grew short of food, water, and
ammunition.
On February 23rd, Marines reached the
top of Mount Suribachi,
and six of them hoisted the flag.
Three did not survive the battle.
The loss of Suribachi was not the end of
the fight.
Japanese positions held out in the north
of Iwo Jima, and only relentless Marine
pressure,
air support, use of flamethrowers, and
weight of numbers carried the day.
In the end, the Japanese did resort to
[music] the banzai charge,
finally closing the battle for Iwo Jima
on March 26th.
Taking the island had cost the Americans
6,800
US dead,
more than a third of the Marine Corps
dead for the whole war.
216 Japanese [music] had been captured
from a garrison of 22,000.
The others were killed in battle,
committed suicide, or hid in the caves
from which they were painstakingly
prized in the years ahead.
The last surrendering in 1949. [music]
The Allies strengthened their forces
they moved towards a more substantial
challenge.
Okinawa, a last stepping stone to the
invasion proper.
Whilst Americans prepared to invade
Japanese soil, on Europe's eastern front
their [music] allies had been
established on enemy soil since January.
At the turn of '44-'45, the Soviets
deployed 6.7 million troops from the
Baltic
to the Adriatic, twice the number that
Germany had unleashed with Barbarossa.
A third of all Soviet infantry and half
of its tank park [music] was
concentrated on two fronts
under Konev and Zhukov astride the road
to Berlin and ready for [music] the
assault.
Konev's offensive opened on 12th [music]
January.
The Soviets unleashed 200 divisions
across the Vistula [music] against the
ruins of Army Group Center.
By the end of the first day, tanks had
broken the front to a penetration of
more than 30 km.
The next day, 3rd Belorussian Front
Chernyakhovsky moved.
On the 14th, 1st Belorussian Front
Zhukov advanced with 2nd Belorussian
Front Rokossovsky alongside him.
Two days later, German troops
garrisoning Warsaw began [music] to
withdraw.
>> Lodz is going to be released. Then they
were transferred to
the Oder.
Oder bridgehead
participated in the capture of Warsaw.
Then straight road
It's not straight like that
[clears throat] on the map, but on the
>> Warsaw fell on the 17th, Krakow on the
18th. In [music] 2 weeks, the Soviet
Army would advance 480 km. The Germans
falling back until the advance paused
with the Russians 80 km from the suburbs
of Berlin.
On January the 20th, elements of Konev's
1st Ukrainian Front crossed the German
border at Namslau.
In north, the 5th Tank and 5th Guards
Armies were making a dash for the Oder.
On January 21st, Hitler created a new
Army Group, Vistula, and gave command
[music] of it to Heinrich Himmler.
The Army Group could boast virtually no
soldiers, only Volkssturm, people's
militia.
So, the fact that Himmler was not a
soldier hardly mattered.
As they advanced, the Red Army liberated
monuments to the philosophy of those who
had occupied their country.
By the time they liberated
Auschwitz-Birkenau on January 27th,
the Red Army had already overrun the
death camps at [music] Treblinka,
Majdanek, Sobibor, and Belzec.
>> I hoped against hope
that when we arrive at Auschwitz, I will
be able to hug my mother.
I don't I was
stood in front of Mengele, he did he was
the tent the main selector
who should live and who should die.
He conducted this button.
He wore white gloves. He was immaculate
in his
uniform.
Shiny high boots.
>> [music]
>> On liberating Auschwitz-Birkenau,
Soviet troops found
368,820
men's suits, 836,255
ladies coats and dresses, and 7 tons of
human hair.
>> [music]
>> A friend of mine that was the first one
to get to Dachau.
He looked at me. He was trying to talk
to me, but started crying. He hugged me.
Said, "I can't tell you about [music]
it." He says, "That's how sad it was."
>> 2 million Germans fled from the invader.
Hitler's Drang nach Osten, thrust to the
east,
had become Flucht aus dem Osten,
flight from the east, reversing the
effects of 800 [music]
years of German settlement.
>> By the beginning of February, Zhukov's
and Konev's fronts were both poised on
the line of the Oder,
>> [music]
>> ready for the final assault.
By mid-February, 8.35 million refugees
were hastening away from the advancing
Red Army.
Some managed to board ship at Baltic
ports to make good their escape.
Thousands boarded the Wilhelm Gustloff
out of Danzig.
It was sunk by a Russian submarine on
January 30th with the loss of at least
eight and possibly 9,000 lives, the
greatest maritime disaster in history.
The day before the sinking of the
Wilhelm Gustloff, Zhukov's 1st
Belorussian Front had crossed the German
border.
Konev was to his south, and both were
bracing for the race to Berlin.
But, both fronts had advanced further
and faster than anticipated
and were outstripping their supply and
support.
They had to pause.
In early February, Chernyakhovsky,
Rokossovsky, and Bagramyan began their
assaults and south of the line, Budapest
fell to the Red Army.
The siege of Budapest had lasted for 50
days from when Soviet forces first
encircled on December 26th, 1944,
trapping 70,000 German and Hungarian
soldiers and over 800,000 civilians.
>> Самая продолжительная
и самая напряжённая.
Много
погибло там [music]
наших.
В том числе и меня сбили там.
Открыл стрельбу ведущий мистер Шмидт.
Отвалил, но меня сбил ведомый. Он зажёг
самолёт.
И когда я вывел из сражения, мне
ударило
в лицо из-под картера.
Ну хорошо, что я был в кожаных
перчатках. Я лицо закрыл
перчатками.
Потом
одну ладонь открыл, то есть оставил,
вторую открыл.
Я уже на парашюте на парашюте начал
скользить, чтоб побыстрее к земле.
И тут у меня мысль такая возникла.
Перед войной
э-э у
>> [sighs]
[music]
>> As their defenses [music] collapsed,
militia from Hungary's fascist Arrow
Cross Party murdered up to 15,000
[music] Jews.
But thousands more who had been
protected by Sweden's special envoy
survived.
The envoy, detained by Soviet forces on
January 17th, disappeared.
His name was Raoul Wallenberg.
The date when Budapest fell, February
the 13th, is also remembered for a
British action on that day, an action
which the British argued was an attempt
to help their Russian allies.
On the night of the 13th-14th February
in Operation Thunderclap, 796
Lancasters of RAF Bomber Command hit
Dresden, a city close to the Soviet line
of advance.
Much of the ancient city was destroyed.
50,000 people were killed.
>> The ground crews reported that on their
way home, Dresden's fires were clearly
visible from over 100 miles away.
>> Disquiet over the destruction is not a
post-war phenomenon.
Churchill himself [music] was disturbed
by an action which did not speed the end
of the war.
But neither, its supporters would argue,
did it delay Germany's collapse.
10 days after Dresden, Rokossovsky
launched his front into Pomerania.
Zhukov joined the offensive on March
1st, and 4 days later, the German
counteroffensive, Spring Awakening, was
launched at the 3rd Ukrainian Front,
General Tolbukhin.
In 4 days, the Germans advanced 25 km,
but were soon turned back. By mid-March,
Spring Awakening was finished,
and Hitler indulged in another round of
sackings and replacements. [music]
By the 6th of April, Malinovsky and
Tolbukhin had reached the outskirts of
Vienna.
The formerly glamorous capital of a
great empire fell on the 13th.
>> [music]
>> All that remained
was the battle for Berlin.
So sure were the allies of victory that
the Yalta Conference was organized for
February.
Two months after attending the [music]
conference, President Roosevelt was dead
of a cerebral hemorrhage. He was 63.
>> All Washington said their last farewell
to the man who had led them for so long
with such wisdom and so great a
sympathy.
>> [music]
>> On the day that [music] Dwight D.
Eisenhower, who would in the years ahead
succeed to the presidency of the United
States of America,
assumed supreme command of Allied ground
[music] troops in Europe, the European
situation appeared to be wholly
favorable.
American Third [music] Army General
Patton was advancing on Metz. The First
Army, General Hodges, was moving towards
Cambrai, and the British Second,
Dempsey, entered Arras.
South Patch's US Seventh, along with the
French Army B, was closing on Lyon,
which [music] was taken on the day that
the British Guards Armoured Division
liberated the Belgian capital, Brussels.
General Montgomery had a plan for an
action that would speed victory.
Eisenhower offered him the use of the
reserve force.
The plan was called Market Garden. Its
intention was to turn the German flank
on the Rhine, seize bridges across that
river, and so facilitate and expedite
the advance.
On September the 17th, Market Garden was
launched.
Market was the airborne operation to
seize the bridges.
Garden was the overland advance by 30th
Corps, General Horrocks, to link up with
the paratroops.
It required, if all went well, the
airborne troops to hold out for 4 days
until the arrival of 30th Corps.
All did not go well.
Many books have been written and films
made about the bridge too far
and the arguments are still pressed
about what went wrong and why.
Montgomery identified the chief problem
as having been the weather.
Always a reliable excuse.
The terrain proved difficult for and
slowed the advance of 30th Corps.
Most of the airborne forces for a
variety of not [music] particularly
convincing reasons were dropped away
from rather than on or at least adjacent
[music] to the bridges they were
designated to take.
At Arnhem, they were dropped between
[music] 8 and 12 km away.
Almost on the heads of Panzer divisions
[music] that were re-equipping.
>> We were over the DZ
and it was red on, stand up, hook up.
Uh green on, go. And out we went.
Feet together, head down, shoulders
round, feet together, watch the ground,
bump. That's it.
>> US 101st Airborne achieved its
objectives with little resistance and
did link with 30th Corps as did 82nd
Airborne.
The bridges at Eindhoven and Nijmegen
were taken.
On the 21st of September, reinforced
German formations recaptured the bridge
at Arnhem, held by the British 1st
Airborne Division.
>> I and what was left of my troop
we went in there on Sunday
and fought from there
until Wednesday afternoon.
And there weren't many of us left then.
Ammunition was
pretty well non-existent by then.
>> On September 26th, the 1st Airborne was
encircled.
Only 2,000 of its 10,000 members escaped
across the Rhine.
>> And I think about 148 dropped.
And there were 10 of us left.
>> The failure of the operation meant that
the war in Europe could not end in 1944.
The day after the loss of 1st Airborne,
Montgomery turned his attention to what
some thought should have been his
[music] first priority.
Clearing the Scheldt Estuary.
The prize vital to the Allied advance
was access to and use of Antwerp.
The large-scale port that the Allies
needed to pump supplies and
reinforcements into their ever-extending
[music]
line.
And could not be used until the Scheldt
Estuary had been cleared and sitting
[music] like a roadblock in the middle
of the Estuary was the island of
Walcheren.
The Canadian First Army began to move on
the north bank of the Scheldt. The
British Second Army was [music] moving
from the southeast.
On October 16th, the Canadian Second
Division took Woensdrecht.
German 15th Army General Gustav von
Zangen was now trapped. [music]
>> They dropped down behind the sand dunes.
And the shells would come down and
so we all got smacked.
I just managed spinning around and
it's in the sand.
And I'm shouting something like uh take
cover.
To to the to the lads and where did they
go?
They ran into the German pillboxes,
didn't they?
With the Germans.
>> [laughter]
>> Not the ones who fired at us
but the ones who were just about to give
up.
>> The Canadians crossed onto Walcheren on
the 3rd of November and the island was
secured by the 8th.
The day that Patton began his offensive
in the Saar.
The French First Army moved on the
Belfort Gap.
By the middle of the month, there were
formations in motion all along the line.
The American First and Ninth Armies to
the north of Patton, elements of the
Seventh entering Strasbourg on the 2nd
and the 6th entering the Maginot Line on
the day that the first vessels entered
and started to use the port of Antwerp.
And then
all hell broke loose.
Operation Herbstnebel Autumn Mist was
unleashed in the Ardennes on December
the 16th, 1944.
History remembers it as the Battle of
the Bulge.
145 km [music] front was held by four
American divisions with one
inexperienced armored division, the 9th,
in support.
Two of the infantry divisions had been
sent to the quiet Ardennes to
recuperate, and a third, the 106th, had
never been in action.
It was onto [music] this force that two
panzer armies fell.
The German 5th Army broke through the
106th Division.
Battle-hardened 28th offered stiffer
resistance.
It was late in the afternoon before
Allied High Command properly realized
what was happening.
Partly due to the confusion sown by 150
Germans who, dressed as Americans,
[music] had infiltrated Allied lines
under the command of Otto Skorzeny, the
man who had rescued Mussolini.
>> Our command was taken totally by
surprise.
So, they reacted
uh
in an extreme.
Everything that could fly flew to bomb
their supply train.
I mean any airplane they could get in
the air went.
And I can remember seeing the sky just
[music] filled with airplanes. It was
really quite a sight.
>> On the 18th, Eisenhower halted the
advance on the Rhine giving priority to
defeating the German offensive.
German onslaught slowed. Fuel was
becoming [music] a problem.
>> When the Bulge broke, they rushed us up
to
>> [music]
>> Belgium to try to get there to help out.
There was three of us in a house trying
to get some sleep.
And as we were there, a bomb came
through and shrapnel was going all over
the place.
I get hit in the leg twice. [music]
And the other fellow There was another
fellow got hit in the chest.
And there was a third guy, we didn't
know what happened to him.
There wasn't a mark on him.
So, we just assumed he died from
concussion.
>> Our outfit was in the Battle of the
Bulge. We were around Bastogne.
We were in a farmhouse.
And I was laying next to a buddy of
mine.
And all of a sudden we hear this
thud.
And it went right between us. We both
laid in like that. It was an 88. But it
didn't go off.
So, I looked over at him and I said,
"Holy snow." He said, "I just did."
>> On the 21st, the commander of the US
101st Airborne in Bastogne,
which had been surrounded,
received a formal demand from the German
commander that his troops surrender.
General Anthony McAuliffe's one-word
formal response [music] was too
difficult for German interpreters, but
priceless for history.
"Nuts." He wrote.
By the 22nd, Sixth Panzer Army had
stopped all together. Units were losing
contact [music] with each other.
Von Manteuffel's Fifth [music] Panzer
Army, which had surrounded Bastogne, was
pushing forward.
But that is as far as the Germans got.
The Third US Army [music] under Patton
now brought pressure from the south and
with the weather clearing, the
overwhelming Allied air supremacy
started to tell.
>> The Third Army was [snorts]
General Patton.
And I remember
during the period where we were under
his command,
he was very big with uh tanks and
armored forces.
We as infantry keeping up with uh those
tanks, well, we were running our tails
off.
>> The Ardennes Offensive cost each side
about 80,000 casualties, losses from
which the Allies could recover.
But not the Axis.
Which was even more the case with losses
[music] in armor and artillery and
aircraft.
>> [music]
>> In the first two months of 1945, the
United States landed [music] seven full
strength divisions in Europe.
Three of them armored.
It took 45 ships to move a single
armored division across the Atlantic.
The scale of the operation comes into
focus.
The Bulge had held up the Allied push
across the Rhine for 6 weeks.
But it had only been held up.
Crossing the Rhine was the last barrier
before Eisenhower's armies poured into
the fatherland.
>> [music]
>> We were going to be the thrust into
mainland Germany.
And all we knew was Germany was across
the river, and we all piddled in the
river for good luck.
>> Patton crossed the Rhine at Oppenheim
the next [music] night. Montgomery
crossed at Emmerich.
And then the US Third Army and then the
Seventh and on the last day of March the
French First Army [music] at
Germersheim.
In less than 4 weeks, Russian and
American and British troops would join
hands [music] on the Elbe. The war in
Europe that had started 68 months
earlier was almost [music] over.
>> [music]
>> Mhm.